"The Pros and Cons of Testing PSA Levels
for Prostate Cancer"
While 64 percent of men
develop hidden prostate cancers
by their 60s,
the lifetime risk of being
diagnosed with prostate cancer
is only about 11 percent,
and the risk of dying from
prostate cancer, 2.5 percent,
at the average age of 80.
So most men develop
prostate cancer
but they die with their tumors
rather than from their tumors.
Most men with prostate cancer
live their whole lives
never knowing they even had it.
That's one of the problems
screening for it.
Many prostate cancers
that are detected
may never have led to harm
even if they'd gone
undiscovered.
Nonetheless,
not all men are so lucky.
About 30,000 Americans die
each year from prostate cancer.
So, should you get a PSA
prostate screening test or not?
PSA stands for
prostate specific antigen,
an enzyme secreted
by cells of the prostate
to liquefy semen
and cervical mucus
to facilitate fertilization.
Elevated levels in the blood can
be a sign of prostate cancer,
which led to FDA approval
as a screening test
for the early detection
of prostate cancer in the 1990s.
If it comes back high,
the test is usually repeated.
If it's still high,
the next step is typically
an ultrasound-guided
biopsy of the prostate
through the rectum.
If there's cancer,
then options include surgery,
radiation, and chemotherapy,
or a delayal of treatment.
However the USPSTF,
the US Preventive Services
Task Force,
the main independent
scientific panel
that sets evidence-based
clinical prevention guidelines,
recommended against
routine PSA screening,
as does the American College
of Preventive Medicine,
the American Academy
of Family Physicians,
and the vast majority,
85 percent of professional
medical societies
in developed countries
around the world, opposed.
In 2018, though,
the USPSTF shifted from
a summary judgement against
to, quote, "the decision about
whether to be screened
for prostate cancer should
be an individual one," unquote,
which is more in line with the
"shared decision making" stance
of the American
Urological Association,
the American College
of Physicians,
and the American Cancer Society.
In other words,
men should be informed
about the risks and benefits
and decide for themselves.
However,
men who are on the fence
and don't express
a clear preference
in favor of screening
should not be screened,
according to the latest
USPSTF recommendations.
More recently, an international
panel of experts concluded
that clinicians
need not feel obligated
to systematically bring it up,
judging that most men would
decide to decline PSA testing,
given the clear harms and
small and uncertain benefits.
That, however, is up to you.
I personally declined,
but let's run the numbers.
Similar to the 92 percent
of women who didn't know
or overestimated the mortality
reduction from mammograms
by tenfold or more,
89 percent of men vastly
overestimated the benefits
of prostate cancer screening
or simply had no idea.
Most thought 50 prostate cancer
deaths could be prevented
out of a thousand men
regularly screened,
when in reality,
it's more like one.
But doesn't even a 1-in-1,000
chance of not dying from cancer
make a few blood tests worth it?
The downsides are more
than inconvenience, though.
About one in seven men
who undergo PSA screening
will test positive,
yet in two-thirds of the cases,
the biopsy results
will be normal.
So out of the thousand men
regularly screened,
about 150 will have
a false alarm
and be biopsied unnecessarily,
which can cause
minor complications
like pain and bloody ejaculate,
or in approximately
1 percent of cases,
more serious complications,
like blood-borne infections
that require hospitalization.
The greatest harm, though,
is overdiagnosis.
Unnecessary biopsies
are bad enough,
but nothing, compared to
unnecessary cancer treatment.
Large-scale randomized trials
suggest that
20 to 50 percent of men
diagnosed with prostate cancer
would have never become
symptomatic in their lifetime.
They never would
have been any wiser
had they not been screened,
but now they may be needlessly
heading to the operating table.
About 3 in 1,000 men die
during or soon after
radical prostatectomy.
That may help explain
why there appears to be
no overall mortality benefit
to prostate cancer screening.
For every life that is saved,
another may be extinguished
for a cancer
they never would have even
known about.
Another 50 in 1,000 men
end up with serious
surgical complications.
Even if the surgery
goes smoothly,
about one in five men develop
long-term urinary incontinence
requiring the use of pads,
and most men--
two out of three--
will experience long-term
erectile dysfunction.
Most men who receive
radiation therapy
also experience long-term
sexual erectile dysfunction
and up to one in six experience
long-term bowel issues
such as fecal incontinence.
If this was saving your life,
it would be worth it,
but over 16 years,
rather than being saved
from a prostate cancer death
by screening,
it may be 25 times more likely
that you were instead
overdiagnosed with a cancer
that wouldn't have bothered you.
Yet you come away
after treatment
thinking the PSA test
saved your life.
It's like with the mammograms.
The people who are
harmed the most--
unnecessary cancer treatment--
feel as though
they've been helped the most.